we are joined by John Kuryakin former
CIA officer and chief of
counterterrorism operations in Pakistan
he was the first CIA official to confirm
the agency's use of torture so John what
was the your role at the CIA and what
were the events that led up to you
blowing the whistle on waterboarding and
then the consequences for that well
really the whole story started in
Pakistan I arrived in Pakistan as the
chief of CIA counterterrorism operations
in January of 2002 and in March of 2002
we got word that Abu Zubaydah was
somewhere in the country in the country
Abu Zubaydah we believed at the time
with the number three in al-qaeda so we
tracked him we hunted him for several
weeks we finally found him and a lot of
al-qaeda fighters many dozens I'm not
allowed to say the real number or the
actual number we captured him and sent
him to a secret prison I'm going to make
a very long story short and tell you
that I went back to CIA headquarters in
the summer of 2002 as soon as I arrived
a senior officer in the CIA's
Counterterrorism Center asked me if I
wanted to be his words certified in the
use of enhanced interrogation techniques
I had never heard the term before so I
asked him what that meant and he
delineate it for me ten different
techniques that we were going to begin
using against prisoners I said that
sounds like a torture program to me but
let me think about it
so I went upstairs to the seventh floor
which is the executive floor of the CIA
and I went to see a very very senior
officer for whom I had worked in the
Middle East about a decade earlier and I
said hey I need to ask some advice they
just asked me downstairs if I want to be
certified in these enhanced
interrogation techniques what do you
think of this and he said first let's
call it what it is is a torture program
they can use any euphemism they want but
this is a torture program second
tortures of slippery slope and you know
how some of these guys are somebody's
going to go overboard and they're going
to kill the prisoner in custody and then
there's going to be a congressional
investigation
and then there's going to be a Justice
Department investigation and somebody's
going to go to prison do you want to go
to prison I said no I don't want to go
to prison ironically I'm the only one
who went to prison but I said no I don't
want a good prison I went back
downstairs and I said this is a torture
program I don't want any part of it and
as it turned out of the 14 people they
asked I was the only one who declined so
I went about my business
on August 1st 2002 the CIA began
torturing Abu Zubaydah at the secret
location other prisoners were also
subsequently tortured but I kept my
mouth shut
now I left the CIA two years later in
2004 and I went into the private sector
in December 2007 right five and a half
years after I was asked if I wanted to
to be trained in these techniques five
and a half years later I get a call from
Brian Ross at ABC News and he said that
he had a source who said that I had
tortured Abu Zubaydah I said that was
absolutely untrue
I had never touched other Zubaydah or
any other prisoner I said your source is
either misinformed or evil liar and well
Brian Ross says you're welcome to come
on the show and defend yourself which I
didn't know was a reporter's trick so I
said I'd think about it
in the meantime President Bush gives a
press conference in which he looks
directly into the camera and says we do
not torture but I knew that was a lie in
fact my wife who is also a senior CIA
officer at the time we were watching
that press conference together and I
turned to her and I said can you believe
this and she said bald-faced liar and
then a few days later he said in
response to a reporter's question well
if there is torture it's the result of a
rogue CIA officer and I said to my wife
Brian Ross's sources at the White House
and they're going to try to pin this on
me so I called Brian Ross and I said
I'll do your interview and I decided in
the lead-up to that interview that no
matter what he asked me
I was going to tell the truth and so I
gave that interview in December 2007
within 24 hours the CIA filed with the
FBI something called a crimes report
indicating that they believed I had
committed a crime the FBI investigated
me from December of 2007 to December of
2008 and then in December 2008 they
dropped the case they closed it and they
determined that I had not committed a
crime what I didn't know was four weeks
later when President Obama was
inaugurated the CIA asked Eric Holder to
secretly reopen the case against me
which they did I didn't know that I was
under investigation for the next four
years and then in January 2012 I was
charged with five felonies including
three counts of espionage what
responsibilities do you think the media
plays or should play and how they
perform in getting out stories from the
White House from sources within the
government and then having an
adversarial role or recently you know
anonymously sourced CIA stories that
russians hacked the 2016 presidential
election yeah I mean how do they perform
with you and how do you see their
responsibilities now this this is such a
tough and complicated issue because
there are so many different and
competing angles involved in it
first let me talk about whistleblowing
because there's a big difference between
whistleblowing and leaking there's
actually a legal definition of
whistleblowing it's bringing to light
any evidence of waste fraud abuse
illegality or threats to the public
health or public safety leaking is just
leaking classified or proprietary
information and people do that for a lot
of different reasons they do it in order
to impact an ongoing debate they do it
to make themselves look good they do it
to kill a program or to damage an
adversary they do it because they love
the excitement of being the guy
providing the information but there's no
benefit to the public health the public
safety there's no targeting of waste
fraud abuse or illegality it's different
so you know while it may be interesting
that for example in a conversation
between President Trump and the Prime
Minister of Australia that Trump was
rude to him and Trump hung up on him the
person who leaked that story within five
or ten minutes of the phone call it's
not reporting on waste fraud abuse or
illegality it's fun it's interesting but
it's not whistleblowing it's a leak and
I can understand any president having
great frustrations with with leaks I
mean nobody was as Nick Sounion besides
Nixon as Barack Obama was but it's my
understanding that the Trump is pretty
upset about leaks too now Obama is you
know he's still held in high regard
people are loving the you know images of
him going on vacation after you as
president we people came to love that of
seeing a president former President
George Bush as well he's known Jimmy
Kimmel Live yeah DeGeneres Show
yeah showing his painting his image
should seem to be rehabilitated and
among the left among liberals potatoes
Bill Maher says you know he was better
than we thought no these were the good
old days why they're the wealth sticking
to Obama he said he doesn't most
transparent administration ever he
couldn't yeah people couldn't Democrat
say well at least he was smarter than
Bush and smarter than McCain and Romney
better we could trust him with lemon I'm
a third-generation Democrat and I am a
die-hard progressive I believed in the
whole hope and change thing it was all a
lie nobody was more an enemy of
transparency than Barack Obama was we
have a law in this country called the
Espionage Act the Espionage Act was
written in 1917 to combat German
saboteurs
it was never updated it doesn't even
mention the words classified information
because the classification system wasn't
invented until the 1950s and it's so
broadly written that in order to commit
espionage a person has to only provide
National Defense information to any
person not entitled to receive it that's
what the law says well that can be
anything or anybody right and so Barack
Obama used it as a political weapon now
between 1917 and 2009 three Americans
were charged with espionage for
providing information to the press just
during the Obama administration he and
Eric Holder prosecuted eight people for
providing information to the press all
charged with espionage espionage is a
grave crime one of the greatest crimes
with which an American can be charged
and in many cases it carries with it the
death penalty so if you want to clamp
down the leaks that's one thing but to
use the Espionage Act to clamp down on
people whose message you don't like you
know Tom Drake is a great example Tom
Drake was a very senior NSA officer very
senior and probably our country's
leading thinker on issues of Internet
privacy
Tom Drake reported exactly the way he
was supposed to up his chain of command
an instance of waste fraud and abuse
right it was a program called thinthread
and he realized that since read while a
complete waste of the taxpayers money
was being doubled back against Americans
and instead of spying on foreign
nationals and on terrorists the NSA was
spying on American citizens so he went
to his supervisor and was told to mind
his own business he then went to the
inspector general and was told the same
thing he complained to the general
counsel and was told he needs to stay
out of it he went to the Pentagon
inspector general because NSA is a
Defense Department agency they destroyed
the evidence that he brought with him
and reported him to the FBI and then he
went to the Congressional Oversight
Committee
to report this waste fraud and abuse now
every single step of the way this is
exactly what you're supposed to do and
what happened to Tom Drake he was
charged with nine felonies including
seven counts of espionage all nine of
those felonies were dismissed but not
until he lost his job he lost his
clearance he lost his family he lost his
pension
he was ruined he's never recovered now
he works at an Apple Store in Maryland
he has never been able to recover
financially socially professionally and
that's what the Obama Justice Department
was trying to do the issue is not let's
Lock this guy up for the rest of his
life
they don't care about that but they care
about making an example of you so if
somebody else sees waste fraud abuse
your illegality they keep their mouth
shut
they say look what happened in John
Kuryakin look what happened at Tom Drake
you know those guys were facing 45 years
in prison they ran up two million dollar
legal bills they lost everything
why would we want to do that we're going
to keep our mouths shut that's the
legacy of Barack Obama couldn't a case
be made because there are people who say
well you went through the legal process
Thomas Drake went through the legal
process the law ultimately works and now
when you had your day in court how did
that play out in terms of okay you had
your chance to present your evidence
Thomas Rowe no no you don't have your
chance to present your evidence because
although we have something called The
Whistleblower Protection Act in this
country national security whistleblowers
are exempt from it so there is no
whistleblower protection if you work in
national security you literally take
your life into your hands that's why in
many cases many people will conclude
that it's better just to keep their
mouth shut
so national security whistleblowers
don't get their day in court and even
when you go through the formal process
you still end up with felony counts now
I didn't go through the formal process
because my formal process created the
CIA's torture program so my choices were
very stark my choices were to keep my
mouth shut or go to the media and I
elected to go to the media what were
your options as far as what evidence you
could was admissible for your court case
and also what kind of testimony you
could get yeah your self I was greatly
hampered by my my judge I was charged in
the Eastern District of Virginia which
is known as the espionage court the
reason it's called the espionage court
is that almost every national security
case is argued in the Eastern District
of Virginia because no national security
defendant has ever won a case there
prosecutors are the ones who win every
case 100% of the time so when we went
with our defense our defense motions to
the judge we made seventy motion these
were 70 different classified documents
that we needed to have Declassified in
order to defend myself so we went to
court we blocked off two days for the
hearings and the judge said that she had
read the motions and she said I'm going
to save everybody a lot of time I'm
denying all 70 motions so the whole
process took about ten minutes not two
days and on the way out of the courtroom
I said to one of my attorneys what just
happened here and you said what just
happened is we have no defense you can't
defend yourself she won't allow you to
defend yourself and I said well what
does that mean and he said that means we
have to talk about a plea well you know
it becomes an economic decision if the
judge won't allow you to defend yourself
because the information is classified
and God forbid you should say something
that's vaguely classified in a court of
law
even if even if the courtroom is closed
and sealed the CIA doesn't want any of
that information out so you can
challenge it and you can appeal to the
Circuit Court of Appeals if you lose
there you can appeal the Supreme Court
but as my attorneys advised me we're
talking about a two or three million
dollar legal bill I already owed them a
million dollars I don't have a total
three or four million dollars to defend
myself
and then the government comes in and
says all right 30 months to do 23 so do
I roll the dice and face 45 years with a
realistic expectation of of 12 to 18 or
but a possibility of as many as 24 years
or do I just take the 23 months and be
done with it
and that's exactly why the government
wins 98 point two percent of its cases
according to Pro Publica because they
heap on these charges friendly judges
don't allow you to defend yourself and
you're faced with this economic decision
you know do I lose my family and risk
dying in prison or do I just take the 23
months and be done with it couldn't we
say that well at least these were
dangerous terrorist suspects you were
dealing with waterboarding could be
necessarily know that how do we know
that opposite a 9/11 night when we were
attacked on 9/11 we were and and which
of the people that we have in custody
was responsible for 9/11 let me tell you
something about other Zubaydah I was a
bait it was not the number three in
al-qaeda I was a beta never joined
al-qaeda he was certainly a bad guy he
ran some safe houses he ran one of the
training camps sure but this man's never
faced his day in court we're supposed to
be a country of laws we're supposed to
be a country that respects his
Constitution that we're supposed to be
this beacon of human rights around the
world and we're not not when we decide
that justice is OK for some people but
from the people we're not going to allow
justice we just put them in Guantanamo
to live the rest of their lives and die
in a cage that's not what the
Constitution's about we're either going
to be a country of laws or we're not and
that's a political decision we have to
make and if we're not we shouldn't bully
the rest of the world to live up to our
standards that's just simply not fair
now if there are terrorists out there
that we capture let's do what Americans
ought to do and put them on trial not
strike them from drones without the
benefit of facing their accusers in the
court of law which we also do to
American citizens I might add let them
face their accusers in court
you